Support Admin Watch on kissasia.cam or kisskh.org
Soporte Admin Mira en kissasia.cam o kisskh.org
[Jibei Palace]
[Palacio Jibei]
[All Rivers Flow into the Sea]
[Todos los ríos desembocan en el mar]
My lord.
Mi señor.
Get up.
Levantarse.
Over the years,
A lo largo de los años,
I've sent countless people
He enviado a innumerables personas
to look for Sage Zhu
para buscar al sabio Zhu
and the Bird Jade Plate.
y el plato de jade de pájaro.
But there has been no news.
Pero no ha habido ninguna novedad.
Yesterday was the day
Ayer fue el día
they were supposed to send back messages.
Se suponía que debían enviar mensajes de respuesta.
But we haven't heard anything
Pero no hemos escuchado nada
from people who went to Shangyi.
de personas que fueron a Shangyi.
Shangyi.
Shang Yi.
It's Ruan Changfeng's team.
Es el equipo de Ruan Changfeng.
He's loyal to you.
Él es leal a ti.
That's not normal.
Eso no es normal.
I think the same as you.
Pienso lo mismo que tú.
I've sent someone to check it out.
He enviado a alguien para que lo compruebe.
Yeah,
Sí,
they were killed.
Fueron asesinados.
They were killed?
¿Los mataron?
Was Sage Zhu
¿Era el sabio Zhu?
in Shangyi?
en Shangyi?
My lord,
Mi señor,
I'll go there right away
Iré allí enseguida
and get him back.
y recuperarlo.
Zhu is dead.
Zhu está muerto.
But the Bird Jade Plate
Pero el plato de jade de pájaro
is missing.
Falta.
I have ordered a mole in Xichuan
Pedí un mole en Xichuan
to put the Bird Jade Plate
para poner el plato de jade de pájaro
in the bounty notice of the Jibei Chamber of Commerce.
en el aviso de recompensa de la Cámara de Comercio de Jibei.
If the person who has the plate
Si la persona que tiene la placa
doesn't know its secrets,
no conoce sus secretos,
he will be attracted
Él se sentirá atraído
by the bounty.
por la generosidad.
What if he knows the secrets of the plate?
¿Y si conoce los secretos del plato?
Then he must want to know
Entonces debe querer saber
what the person who posted the bounty notice wanted to do.
Lo que la persona que publicó el aviso de recompensa quería hacer.
So,
Entonces,
he will definitely appear
Definitivamente aparecerá
in Xichuan.
en Xichuan.
Got it.
Entiendo.
[Liu Yunting, Jibei Palace]
[Liu Yunting, Palacio Jibei]
I'll go to Xichuan
Iré a Xichuan
right away.
de inmediato.
[Treasure at Dawn] ♪Reach the highest level♪
[Tesoro al amanecer] ♪Alcanza el nivel más alto♪
♪Reach the state of no desire, illuminate the virtuous light♪
♪Alcanza el estado de no deseo, ilumina la luz virtuosa♪
♪Man is upright because he is moral, and he is strong because he is upright♪
♪El hombre es recto porque es moral, y es fuerte porque es recto♪
♪Upright, strong, and fair♪
♪Recto, fuerte y justo♪
♪I am the fire♪
♪Yo soy el fuego♪
♪Burning out all desires♪
♪Quemando todos los deseos♪
♪River can't put me out♪
♪El río no puede apagarme♪
♪Yang's beginning leads to development. Wu Chi creates Tai Chi♪
♪El comienzo de Yang conduce al desarrollo. Wu Chi crea el Tai Chi♪
♪People mistake their bodily form, forgetting the true mind within♪
♪La gente confunde su forma corporal, olvidando la verdadera mente que hay en su interior♪
♪People make their own enemies♪
♪La gente crea sus propios enemigos♪
♪Books are all about reason. People are full of purpose♪
♪Los libros son pura razón. La gente tiene un propósito.♪
♪People are overrun by illusions♪
♪La gente está invadida por ilusiones♪
♪They are fascinated by illusions♪
♪Están fascinados por las ilusiones♪
♪With a pure mind, sitting in the clouds♪
♪Con una mente pura, sentado en las nubes♪
♪Watching people creating dreams♪
♪Observando a la gente crear sueños♪
♪Is it painful to live in the world?♪
♪¿Es doloroso vivir en el mundo?♪
♪Learn from nature. Forget all your desires♪
Aprende de la naturaleza. Olvida todos tus deseos.
♪How about clearing all my thoughts?♪
♪¿Qué tal si aclaras todos mis pensamientos?♪
♪Moths fly into the fire♪
♪Las polillas vuelan hacia el fuego♪
♪The fire melts old shackles♪
♪El fuego derrite viejos grilletes♪
♪Today, I know it's me♪
♪Hoy sé que soy yo♪
[Treasure at Dawn]
[Tesoro al amanecer]
[Episode 10] [Lin's Mansion Hides Secrets, Breakwall Reveals the Murderer]
[Episodio 10] [La mansión de Lin esconde secretos, Breakwall revela al asesino]
He killed the Chairman Song. Arrest him.
Él mató al presidente Song. Arréstenlo.
Don't slander me.
No me calumnies.
I didn't kill the Chairman Song.
Yo no maté al Presidente Song.
Arrest him.
Arréstalo.
Qin Shi.
Qin Shi.
You'd better admit it
Será mejor que lo admitas.
and give up.
y rendirse.
Otherwise, your family will be implicated.
De lo contrario, su familia se verá implicada.
Admit it.
Admítelo.
We go way back.
Nos conocemos desde hace mucho tiempo.
I won't torture you.
No te torturaré.
Die.
El.
Stop.
Detener.
Do you want to kill the witness?
¿Quieres matar al testigo?
It's an internal affair of our Jibei Chamber of Commerce.
Es un asunto interno de nuestra Cámara de Comercio de Jibei.
Mind your own business.
Ocúpate de tus propios asuntos.
Chairman Li, you'd better find out the truth.
Presidente Li, será mejor que averigüe la verdad.
It's a matter of human life.
Es una cuestión de vida humana.
Don't kill the wrong person.
No mates a la persona equivocada.
Shall we take him back for interrogation?
¿Lo llevamos de nuevo para interrogarlo?
Take him away.
Llevatelo lejos.
Honey.
Miel.
Do you think Qin Shi is the murderer?
¿Crees que Qin Shi es el asesino?
Admit it.
Admítelo.
You're tough.
Eres duro
Mr. Chairman.
Señor Presidente.
He's tough.
Él es duro.
If you can't get him to admit it, it means you're useless.
Si no logras que lo admita significa que eres inútil.
I don't need useless people.
No necesito gente inútil.
Okay.
Bueno.
Got it.
Entiendo.
You're tough, huh?
Eres duro, ¿eh?
Let's see what's tougher, you or it.
Veamos qué es más difícil, tú o eso.
If you torture him again,
Si lo torturas de nuevo,
he'll die.
Él morirá.
Do you want to torture him into confessing?
¿Quieres torturarlo para que confiese?
Come on.
Vamos.
It's an interrogation technique.
Es una técnica de interrogatorio.
We're not torturing him into confessing.
No lo estamos torturando para que confiese.
He shouldn't have been tortured.
No debería haber sido torturado.
But he was interrogated all night
Pero lo interrogaron toda la noche.
and said nothing.
y no dijo nada.
Did he say nothing,
¿No dijo nada?
or did you not want him to say it?
¿O no querías que lo dijera?
What do you mean, Gu?
¿Qué quieres decir, Gu?
Chairman Li.
Presidente Li.
Do you mind
Te importa
if I talk to Qin Shi alone?
¿Qué pasa si hablo con Qin Shi a solas?
Qin Shi.
Qin Shi.
Answer a few questions.
Responda algunas preguntas.
I didn't...
Yo no...
I didn't kill the Chairman Song.
Yo no maté al Presidente Song.
I hope it was not you.
Espero que no hayas sido tú.
Please tell me in detail
Por favor dímelo en detalle
what happened that night.
¿Qué pasó esa noche?
That night...
Esa noche...
Mr. Chairman.
Señor Presidente.
What happened?
¿Qué pasó?
It's not a big deal.
No es gran cosa
Don't worry about him.
No te preocupes por él.
Chase him.
Persíguelo.
Mr. Chairman.
Señor Presidente.
Who's there?
¿Quién está ahí?
Honey.
Miel.
You're awake.
Estás despierto.
Honey, how...?
Cariño, ¿cómo...?
How did I get back?
¿Cómo volví?
You walked back.
Caminaste de regreso.
You came back covered in blood.
Regresaste cubierto de sangre.
I changed your clothes
Te cambié la ropa
and found it was not your blood.
y descubrí que no era tu sangre.
What's wrong?
¿Qué ocurre?
Have you forgotten all about it?
¿Te has olvidado por completo de ello?
I walked back?
¿Caminé de regreso?
Why does the bell keep ringing?
¿Por qué sigue sonando la campana?
It's the alarm bell of the Jibei Chamber of Commerce.
Es la campana de alarma de la Cámara de Comercio de Jibei.
One peal of bells,
Un repique de campanas,
the rangers return.
Los guardabosques regresan.
Two peals of bells,
Dos campanadas,
friends come.
Vienen amigos.
Three peals of bells,
Tres campanadas,
enemies come.
Los enemigos vienen.
Four peals...
Cuatro campanadas...
All right. Just drink it.
Está bien. Sólo bébelo.
Honey.
Miel.
How many times
¿Cuántas veces?
did the bell ring?
¿sonó la campana?
Eight times.
Ocho veces.
What does it mean?
¿Qué significa?
Eight peals of bells,
Ocho campanadas,
an elder is dead.
Un anciano ha muerto.
Eight peals
Ocho campanadas
of bells
de campanas
mean someone important is dead.
significa que alguien importante está muerto.
I'm afraid you and Chairman Song
Me temo que tú y el presidente Song
were poisoned
fueron envenenados
when you first saw the painting.
Cuando viste el cuadro por primera vez.
Everything you encountered
Todo lo que encontraste
was your illusion,
fue tu ilusion,
just like us.
Igual que nosotros.
We've looked into it.
Lo hemos investigado.
You were the only person there
Eras la única persona allí
besides Chairman Song that night.
Además del presidente Song esa noche.
You don't remember what happened later
No recuerdas lo que pasó después
because of datura flowers.
por las flores de datura.
Was it me
¿Fui yo?
who killed the Chairman?
¿Quién mató al presidente?
Thank you for your justice.
Gracias por tu justicia.
I'm sorry about earlier.
Lo siento por lo de antes.
Welcome to the Chamber of Commerce for tea.
Bienvenidos a la Cámara de Comercio para tomar el té.
Here we go again.
Aquí vamos de nuevo.
Should you
¿Deberías?
finish what you didn't do?
¿Terminar lo que no hiciste?
I'll do my best.
Haré lo mejor que pueda.
I won't let you down.
No te defraudaré.
If you fail again,
Si vuelves a fallar,
burn yourself.
quemarse
Chairman Li
Presidente Li
is generous on the surface.
Es generoso en la superficie.
We found out the murderer.
Descubrimos al asesino.
But he didn't give us any reward.
Pero no nos dio ninguna recompensa.
If it wasn't for me,
Si no fuera por mí,
you might not have made it out
Puede que no lo hayas logrado
of the Jibei Chamber of Commerce.
de la Cámara de Comercio de Jibei.
Don't expect rewards.
No esperes recompensas
Even though you saved me,
Aunque me salvaste,
you don't have to mention it every time.
No es necesario mencionarlo cada vez.
Have you seen Qin Shi?
¿Has visto a Qin Shi?
How's it going?
¿Cómo estás?
He was also poisoned with datura flowers.
También fue envenenado con flores de datura.
It causes hallucinations.
Provoca alucinaciones.
He was alone with the Chairman Song.
Estaba solo con el presidente Song.
He should be the murderer.
Él debería ser el asesino.
What is he eating?
¿Qué está comiendo?
Didn't you notice
¿No te diste cuenta?
that you hit us?
¿que nos pegaste?
I'm sorry.
Lo lamento.
Someone is selling the great painter Li Ye's paintings.
Alguien está vendiendo las pinturas del gran pintor Li Ye.
I'm in a rush.
Tengo prisa.
I'm sorry.
Lo lamento.
Those painters are not good at painting.
Esos pintores no son buenos pintando.
But they are good at making money.
Pero son buenos para ganar dinero.
The times are degenerating.
Los tiempos se están degenerando.
The people are corrupted.
El pueblo está corrompido.
Let's have a look.
Echemos un vistazo.
Out of the way.
Fuera del camino.
These are all mine.
Estos son todos mios.
What are you?
¿Qué vas a?
Um.
Uno.
What kind of painting is this?
¿Qué tipo de pintura es ésta?
I want one.
Quiero uno.
What painting is this?
¿Qué cuadro es éste?
This painting...
Esta pintura...
Are there any other paintings?
¿Hay otros cuadros?
Have a look.
Echa un vistazo.
Since joining the Jibei Chamber of Commerce,
Desde que me uní a la Cámara de Comercio de Jibei,
I've been the Chairman's bodyguard.
He sido el guardaespaldas del presidente.
Now,
Ahora,
I killed him.
Lo maté.
How am I supposed
¿Cómo se supone que lo haga?
to live?
¿vivir?
Mr. Chairman.
Señor Presidente.
This should be the murder weapon.
Esta debería ser el arma homicida.
Nice sword.
Bonita espada.
What a pity.
Qué lástima.
Keep it sealed
Mantenlo sellado
as physical evidence.
como evidencia física.
Yes.
Sí.
I've been on adventures for years.
He estado en aventuras durante años.
I've never seen
Nunca he visto
such a sharp weapon.
Un arma tan afilada.
Gu Tian.
Gu Tian.
You're kind of an expert on weapons.
Eres una especie de experto en armas.
Analyze it.
Analizarlo
Could Qin Shi's sword
¿Podría la espada de Qin Shi?
cut Song Jingye into pieces
cortó a Song Jingye en pedazos
in an instant?
¿en seguida?
Besides, the wounds are smooth,
Además, las heridas son suaves,
with no scars.
Sin cicatrices.
No way.
De ninguna manera.
That sword is not the murder weapon.
Esa espada no es el arma homicida.
Qin Shi is not the murderer.
Qin Shi no es el asesino.
Then who is the murderer?
Entonces ¿quién es el asesino?
Wait.
Esperar.
It's not right.
No está bien.
Think again.
Piénsalo otra vez.
What's so weird about it?
¿Qué tiene esto de raro?
Weird?
¿Extraño?
Speaking of weird things,
Hablando de cosas raras,
the painting is the most weird.
El cuadro es lo más raro.
But we've found out
Pero lo hemos descubierto
the secret of the painting.
El secreto de la pintura.
Didn't you say that people who entered
¿No dijiste que la gente que entraba?
were hallucinating
estaban alucinando
because the people below
porque la gente de abajo
lit the charcoal?
¿encendiste el carbón?
Charcoal.
Carbón.
That's right.
Así es.
Charcoal. That's right.
Carbón. Así es.
I know what the problem is.
Sé cuál es el problema.
The mansion has been abandoned for five years.
La mansión ha estado abandonada durante cinco años.
But there was plenty of charcoal.
Pero había mucho carbón.
And the mansion is well-preserved.
Y la mansión está bien conservada.
Most importantly,
Lo más importante es que
there are no broken doors.
No hay puertas rotas.
This is the weirdest point.
Éste es el punto más extraño.
Are you saying
¿Estas diciendo?
that the mansion looks abandoned,
que la mansión parece abandonada,
but it's not,
pero no lo es,
and there are people living in it?
¿Y hay gente viviendo allí?
That explains
Eso lo explica
why everyone who enters
¿Por qué todos los que entran?
gets poisoned.
se envenena.
It shows that someone inside was up to something.
Esto demuestra que alguien dentro estaba tramando algo.
Your Excellency, I didn't know it was you.
Excelencia, no sabía que era usted.
I'm sorry.
Lo lamento.
[Like the Rising Sun] Sage Zhu, whom His Excellency has been looking for years,
[Como el Sol Naciente] El sabio Zhu, a quien Su Excelencia ha estado buscando durante años,
died in Shangyi.
Murió en Shangyi.
His Excellency ordered you to post a bounty notice
Su Excelencia le ordenó publicar un aviso de recompensa.
about the Bird Jade Plate.
Acerca del plato de jade de pájaro.
Li Zhizhuo,
Li Zhizhuo,
you know what to do next, right?
Sabes qué hacer a continuación, ¿verdad?
I know.
Lo sé.
No matter who has the jade plate,
No importa quién tenga la placa de jade,
if he wants money,
Si quiere dinero,
he will take the bait.
Él morderá el anzuelo.
You're not that stupid.
No eres tan estúpido
Your Excellency.
Su Excelencia.
There's one more thing.
Hay una cosa más.
The traitor we've been looking for years
El traidor que hemos estado buscando durante años
appeared in the Lin's Mansion.
apareció en la Mansión Lin.
Do you want me to take him down?
¿Quieres que lo baje?
The Treasure of the Sealed Book is important.
El Tesoro del Libro Sellado es importante.
Do what you have to do.
Haz lo que tengas que hacer.
Don't meddle
No te entrometas
in anything else.
en cualquier otra cosa.
Yes.
Sí.
Your Excellency.
Su Excelencia.
I've been working
He estado trabajando
for the organization in Xichuan for years.
para la organización en Xichuan durante años.
When can I return to the lord?
¿Cuando podré volver al señor?
Are you saying that Qin Shi may not be the murderer?
¿Estás diciendo que Qin Shi puede no ser el asesino?
There is a mysterious person in this mansion.
Hay una persona misteriosa en esta mansión.
To solve this case,
Para resolver este caso,
the person is the breakthrough.
La persona es el gran avance.
Your finger is cut.
Tienes el dedo cortado.
What is that?
¿Qué es eso?
The dust of Star Gold.
El polvo de estrella dorada.
Why is this thing here?
¿Por qué está esto aquí?
It must be from the murder weapon.
Debe ser del arma homicida.
Who's so rich
¿Quién es tan rico?
that he used Star Gold to make a weapon?
¿que usó Star Gold para hacer un arma?
Do you remember
Te acuerdas
what Qin Shi said?
¿Qué dijo Qin Shi?
Song Jingye and Qin Shi
Song Jingye y Qin Shi
chased up to the second floor.
Perseguido hasta el segundo piso.
But he died on the ground floor.
Pero murió en la planta baja.
It means
Eso significa
there's something wrong with the roof.
Hay algo mal con el techo.
Let's go up and have a look.
Vamos a subir y echar un vistazo.
Look.
Mirar.
There are indentation marks in the wood.
Hay marcas de hendiduras en la madera.
Normal nets
Redes normales
can't bear the weight.
No puedo soportar el peso.
And the net is strong.
Y la red es fuerte.
After listening to you,
Después de escucharte,
it's possible.
Es posible.
You need to get the Western tussah silk.
Necesitas conseguir la seda tussah occidental.
Then, weave it into a net.
Luego, tejerlo hasta formar una red.
To leave
Salir
such a deep mark,
una marca tan profunda,
you need to cover it with the dust of Star Gold.
Necesitas cubrirlo con el polvo de Estrella Dorada.
Tussah silk.
Seda tussah.
Star Gold.
Estrella de oro.
Do you have an idea?
¿Tienes alguna idea?
He's rich.
Él es rico.
Wen Jue.
Wen Jue.
Where does your Lord's Mansion
¿Dónde está la Mansión de vuestro Señor?
sell your Star Gold
vende tu Estrella de Oro
every year?
¿cada año?
Even if you have just come to Xichuan,
Incluso si acabas de llegar a Xichuan,
you know Star Gold is expensive.
Ya sabes que Star Gold es caro.
Many people
Mucha gente
risked their lives
arriesgaron sus vidas
to take it and leave Xichuan.
tomarlo y dejar Xichuan.
If you ask me who has it,
Si me preguntas quién lo tiene,
all I can say
Todo lo que puedo decir
is that anyone could have it.
Es que cualquiera podría tenerlo.
It's about ten meters high.
Mide unos diez metros de altura.
Song Jingye fell
Song Jingye sobre
from a height of only ten meters.
desde una altura de sólo diez metros.
Even if it were wrapped in Star Gold and Tussah Silk,
Incluso si estuviera envuelto en oro estrella y seda Tussah,
considering the height,
teniendo en cuenta la altura,
he shouldn't have been cut so neatly.
No debería haber sido cortado tan limpiamente.
Unless
A menos que
he weighs 500kg.
Él pesa 500 kg.
That means
Eso significa
the murderer must've pushed him down hard,
El asesino debió empujarlo con fuerza.
making him fall quickly.
Haciéndole caer rápidamente.
Gu Tian.
Gu Tian.
Can you
Puede
do it?
¿hazlo?
Are you crazy?
¿Estás loco?
If I were that good,
Si yo fuera tan bueno,
I'd just kill Song Jingye.
Simplemente mataría a Song Jingye.
I wouldn't do that much work.
Yo no haría tanto trabajo.
I must have missed something.
Debo haberme perdido algo.
Let's look for it.
Vamos a buscarlo.
Look.
Mirar.
Each mark
Cada marca
is between the first and second floors,
está entre el primer y segundo piso,
and the height is basically the same.
y la altura es básicamente la misma.
But this crack
Pero esta grieta
is different.
es diferente
It looks
Se ve
like a drag mark.
como una marca de arrastre.
Why?
¿Por qué?
Look, guys.
Miren, muchachos.
I think there was something here.
Creo que había algo aquí.
Be careful.
Ten cuidado.
Someone did something to this railing.
Alguien le hizo algo a esta barandilla.
What does that mean?
¿Qué significa eso?
It means
Eso significa
that with Song Jingye's weight,
Que con el peso de Song Jingye,
even if he fell at this height,
Aunque cayera a esta altura,
he wouldn't have
Él no lo habría hecho
been cut so neatly.
Fue cortado tan cuidadosamente.
It's like
Es como
someone formidably strong
alguien formidablemente fuerte
threw several blades at Song Jingye at the same time
Lanzó varias espadas a Song Jingye al mismo tiempo.
and cut him into pieces easily.
y cortarlo en pedazos fácilmente.
I see.
Veo.
[Fair and Square]
[Justo y cuadrado]
Look.
Mirar.
It's weird
Es raro
that these two stone lions are here.
que estos dos leones de piedra están aquí.
The point is
El punto es
that this base is the same size
que esta base es del mismo tamaño
as the square mark
como la marca cuadrada
upstairs.
piso superior.
So,
Entonces,
it should have been placed upstairs.
Debería haber sido colocado arriba.
You think
Crees
the murderer put the trap
El asesino puso la trampa
on the lion.
sobre el león.
Then, he pushed the lion down from above
Luego empujó al león hacia abajo desde arriba.
to drive the tussah silk
Para conducir la seda tussah
to Song Jingye, right?
A Song Jingye, ¿verdad?
Right.
Bien.
Young Mistress.
Joven amante.
This lion weighs at least 400kg.
Este león pesa al menos 400 kg.
Even the three of us can't move it easily.
Ni siquiera nosotros tres podemos moverlo fácilmente.
Knock it down.
Derribarlo.
Me?
¿A mí?
You think very highly of me.
Piensas muy bien de mí.
Dig a hole next to it.
Cava un hoyo al lado.
Then, get below it and push.
Luego, colócate debajo y empuja.
It should fall
Debería caer
easily.
fácilmente.
Mozi said,
Mozi dijo:
"Add weight"
"Añadir peso"
"to one end of a beam,"
"a un extremo de una viga",
"the beam will tilt."
"El haz se inclinará."
"The post and the weight doesn't match."
"El poste y el peso no coinciden".
"If the beam is balance,"
"Si la viga está en equilibrio,"
"the end with the post is short, and the end with the weight is long."
"El extremo con el poste es corto y el extremo con el peso es largo."
"If you add the same weight to both ends,"
"Si añades el mismo peso a ambos extremos",
"the end with the post will go down,"
"El final con el poste se irá abajo",
"and the post gains more weight."
"y el post gana más peso."
I only understood the first half.
Sólo entendí la primera mitad.
That's enough.
Eso es suficiente.
Come and knock it down.
Ven y derríbalo.
When it comes to hard labor,
Cuando se trata de trabajos duros,
you think of me.
Piensas en mí.
Can we count on your brain?
¿Podemos contar con tu cerebro?
See?
¿Ver?
It's so hard.
Es muy difícil.
What about now?
¿Y ahora qué?
There should have
Debería haber
been four balls under it
Han sido cuatro bolas debajo de él
in the four holes.
en los cuatro agujeros.
It corresponds to the four grooves upstairs.
Corresponde a las cuatro ranuras del piso superior.
In that case, a healthy man
En ese caso, un hombre sano
can move the stone lion easily.
Puede mover el león de piedra fácilmente.
Not to mention
Sin mencionar
a master with great internal power.
Un maestro con un gran poder interno.
Where are the balls?
¿Dónde están las bolas?
They must have been smashed when it fell.
Debieron quedar aplastados cuando cayó.
How do you know that?
¿Cómo lo sabes?
It's easy.
Es fácil.
It's the same as treating a patient.
Es lo mismo que tratar a un paciente.
It's about observation, auscultation and olfaction, inquiry, and palpation.
Se trata de observación, auscultación, olfacción, indagación y palpación.
After we entered the Lin's Mansion,
Después de que entramos en la Mansión Lin,
we found that the two stone lions
Encontramos que los dos leones de piedra
were placed wrongly.
fueron colocados incorrectamente.
I knew there was something wrong with it.
Sabía que había algo mal con ello.
This is "observation".
Esto es "observación".
Then, we entered the building.
Luego entramos al edificio.
I smelled blood on the beam.
Olí sangre en la viga.
So, I deduced
Entonces, lo deduje.
that Song Jingye died nearby,
que Song Jingye murió cerca,
and
y
he was cut into pieces in the air.
Fue cortado en pedazos en el aire.
This is "auscultation and olfaction".
Esto es "auscultación y olfacción".
Then, we solved the secret
Entonces, resolvimos el secreto.
about the Golden Monkey.
Sobre el Mono Dorado.
So, we were not confused
Así que no estábamos confundidos.
by the visions of the mansion.
por las visiones de la mansión.
This is "inquiry".
Esto es "investigación".
The most important one
El más importante
is "palpation".
es "palpación".
Can you feel the mansion's pulse?
¿Puedes sentir el pulso de la mansión?
If this mansion was human,
Si esta mansión fuera humana,
it would have wailed in pain.
Habría gemido de dolor.
Let's go in again.
Entremos de nuevo.
Who
OMS
set up
configuración
this trap?
¿Esta trampa?
The trap
La trampa
was not improvised.
No fue improvisado.
Only by forcing this mysterious person to show up
Sólo obligando a esta misteriosa persona a aparecer
can we know the truth.
¿Podemos conocer la verdad?
Do you have a plan?
¿Tienes un plan?
He's trying his best
Él está haciendo lo mejor que puede
to turn Lin's Mansion into a haunted mansion
Convertir la Mansión Lin en una mansión embrujada
because he doesn't want people to come in.
Porque no quiere que la gente entre.
He wants to live here comfortably.
Él quiere vivir aquí cómodamente.
If we destroy the mansion,
Si destruimos la mansión,
he will show up.
Él aparecerá.
What just passed?
¿Qué acaba de pasar?
It's a person.
Es una persona.
Chase.
Perseguir.
I'll go get Jiu.
Iré a buscar a Jiu.
Be careful, you guys.
¡Tened cuidado, muchachos!
Okay.
Bueno.
There he is.
Ahí está.
We've taken the painting away.
Nos hemos llevado el cuadro.
The monkey is gone again.
El mono se ha ido otra vez.
Are we
¿Somos nosotros?
poisoned again?
¿Envenenado de nuevo?
I smelled kerosene.
Olí a queroseno.
Be careful.
Ten cuidado.
Run.
Correr.
Looks like the person behind this is about to reveal himself.
Parece que la persona detrás de esto está a punto de revelarse.
Come on.
Vamos.
Gu Tian.
Gu Tian.
Show a part of your body.
Muestra una parte de tu cuerpo.
Let's see if we can seduce him to attack.
Veamos si podemos seducirlo para que ataque.
Okay.
Bueno.
Why don't you do it?
¿Por qué no lo haces?
I'm a physician.
Soy medico
If you're injured,
Si estás herido,
I can bandage you to stop the bleeding.
Puedo vendarte para detener el sangrado.
If I'm injured,
Si estoy lesionado,
you will watch me die.
Me verás morir.
That's right.
Así es.
Be careful.
Ten cuidado.
Did you see it?
¿Lo viste?
Yes.
Sí.
Go.
Ir.
Are you all right?
¿Estás bien?
I'm lucky.
Tengo suerte.
It's not poisonous.
No es venenoso
My clothes...
Mi ropa...
Go.
Ir.
Gu Tian.
Gu Tian.
There is no light here.
No hay luz aquí
It's not good for us.
No es bueno para nosotros.
We can't go on like this.
No podemos seguir así.
I have a good thing.
Tengo algo bueno.
Do you want to have a try?
¿Quieres intentarlo?
What's that?
¿Qué es eso?
It can temporarily enhance your five senses.
Puede mejorar temporalmente tus cinco sentidos.
After eating it,
Después de comerlo,
you can see night as day.
Puedes ver la noche como el día.
Why don't you eat it?
¿Por qué no lo comes?
It's not perfect.
No es perfecto
Its properties are unstable.
Sus propiedades son inestables.
Why?
¿Por qué?
You'll see.
Ya verás.
How about it?
¿Qué tal?
How do you feel?
¿Cómo te sientes?
I'll see
Ya veré
who you are.
Quién eres.
You're vicious.
Eres cruel
You wanted to kill us without saying anything.
Querías matarnos sin decir nada.
Too bad
Demasiado
I didn't get to kill you.
No pude matarte
I've been away from the Breakwall
He estado lejos del Breakwall
for years.
durante años.
I hid from you.
Me escondí de ti.
But you
Pero tú
wouldn't let me go.
No me dejaría ir.
You...
Tú...
Don't talk.
No hables
Let me do the talk.
Déjame hablar.
Okay.
Bueno.
Now that you know who we are,
Ahora que ya sabes quiénes somos,
you know
sabes
why we are here.
Por qué estamos aquí.
Believe it or not,
Por extraño que parezca,
I didn't say anything
No dije nada
about that year.
Sobre ese año.
Whether we believe it or not
Lo creamos o no
is not up to you.
No depende de ti.
What do you want to do?
¿Qué es lo que quieres hacer?
He knows a secret method.
Él conoce un método secreto.
He'll pierce a gold needle into your body.
Perforará tu cuerpo con una aguja de oro.
Holding the gold needle,
Sosteniendo la aguja de oro,
he can tell
Él puede decirlo
if you're lying.
Si estás mintiendo.
Nothing will happen if you're telling the truth.
No pasará nada si dices la verdad.
If you're lying...
Si estás mintiendo...
What will happen?
¿Qué pasará?
The gold needle will follow your blood
La aguja de oro seguirá tu sangre.
and go all the way into your brain.
y llegar hasta tu cerebro.
What do you think will happen?
¿Qué crees que pasará?
Kill me if you want to.
Mátame si quieres.
Why bother?
¿Por qué molestarse?
If you're not afraid to die,
Si no tienes miedo a morir,
why are you hiding here?
¿Por qué te escondes aquí?
You're being ridiculous.
Estás siendo ridículo.
I don't know that.
No lo sé.
Go.
Ir.
Feel him out.
Sientelo.
Not bad.
Nada mal.
Your pulse is stable.
Su pulso es estable.
Go ahead.
Adelante.
Tell us
Cuéntanos
what the Breakwall is.
Qué es el Breakwall.
You don't know the Breakwall?
¿No conoces el Breakwall?
Don't talk nonsense.
No digas tonterías
We want to know if you're lying.
Queremos saber si estás mintiendo.
Answer my question.
Responde mi pregunta.
The Breakwall
El muro de contención
was a mysterious organization
era una organización misteriosa
in Jibei.
en Jibei.
Lord Su Rang
Señor Su Rang
and four other sages
y otros cuatro sabios
served the Jibei Mansion.
sirvió en la Mansión Jibei.
Right.
Bien.
Tell me about that year.
Cuéntame sobre ese año.
I was nobody
Yo no era nadie
in the Breakwall.
en el Rompeolas.
There were a lot of things
Había muchas cosas
I didn't know.
No lo sabía.
I knew
Yo lo sabía
there was a rebellion
Hubo una rebelión
in the Jibei Mansion.
en la Mansión Jibei.
But very soon,
Pero muy pronto,
Jibei King
Rey Jibei
calmed the unrest
calmó los disturbios
with the help of our lord.
con la ayuda de nuestro señor.
Since then,
Desde entonces,
the young king
el joven rey
has changed his temperament.
Ha cambiado su temperamento.
He spent every day in a daze.
Pasaba todos los días aturdido.
He even let our lord
Incluso dejó que nuestro señor
take care
cuidarse
of court affairs.
de asuntos judiciales.
Why did you run away?
¿Por qué huiste?
That year,
Ese año,
most of the people in our organization
la mayoría de las personas en nuestra organización
who were involved in this
que estuvieron involucrados en esto
were killed.
fueron asesinados.
I was afraid of being killed.
Tenía miedo de que me mataran.
So, I found a way
Entonces encontré una manera
to escape from the Breakwall.
para escapar del Rompemuros.
I used a painting
Utilicé una pintura
to fake my death to escape.
Fingir mi muerte para escapar.
Does Song Jingye's death
¿La muerte de Song Jingye?
have anything to do with you?
¿tiene algo que ver contigo?
Kind of.
Un poco.
But
Pero
I just gave the murderer
Acabo de darle al asesino
a hand.
una mano.
Why?
¿Por qué?
I thought
Pensé
the Breakwall sent him to kill me.
El Breakwall lo envió a matarme.
The Cloud-shaped Jade.
El jade en forma de nube.
Why do you have it?
¿Porque lo tienes?
I found it
Lo encontré
where Song Jingye died.
donde murió Song Jingye.
I knew it was precious.
Sabía que era precioso.
I wanted
Yo quería
to give it to Her Excellency.
para entregárselo a Su Excelencia.
I don't know
No sé
if she will spare my life.
Si ella me perdona la vida.
Who are you?
¿Quién eres?
Senior.
Sénior.
You're injured.
Estás herido.
Now that the fish is hooked,
Ahora que el pez está enganchado,
it's time to catch it.
Es hora de atraparlo.
[The animals in the show are props]
[Los animales del espectáculo son accesorios]
[No animals were harmed during the filming]
[Ningún animal resultó dañado durante el rodaje]
♪Under the sky, light and shadow go together♪
♪Bajo el cielo, la luz y la sombra van juntas♪
♪The reflection of prosperity and splendor♪
♪El reflejo de la prosperidad y el esplendor♪
♪Hides many secrets♪
♪Esconde muchos secretos♪
♪It's like♪
♪Es como♪
♪Every page of your life♪
♪Cada página de tu vida♪
♪It's all about destiny♪
♪Todo es cuestión del destino♪
♪The story has tragedy and comedy♪
♪La historia tiene tragedia y comedia♪
♪To discover the mystery♪
♪Para descubrir el misterio♪
♪We go on adventures♪
♪Nos vamos de aventuras♪
♪We don't run away or compromise easily♪
♪No huimos ni nos comprometemos fácilmente♪
♪When dawn comes♪
♪Cuando llega el amanecer♪
♪The light shines♪
♪La luz brilla♪
♪We follow the path of discovery♪
♪Seguimos el camino del descubrimiento♪
♪To chase and welcome♪
♪Para perseguir y dar la bienvenida♪
♪Every unknown story♪
♪Cada historia desconocida♪
♪We take a trip together♪
♪Hacemos un viaje juntos♪
♪With hot blood and original purpose♪
♪Con sangre caliente y propósito original♪
♪We seize the day and live it to the fullest♪
♪Aprovechamos el día y lo vivimos al máximo♪
♪Leave a mark on our journey♪
♪Deja una huella en nuestro viaje♪
♪Scatter the darkness with our hearts♪
♪Dispersa la oscuridad con nuestros corazones♪
♪Aspire to make a difference♪
♪Aspira a marcar la diferencia♪
♪To discover the mystery♪
♪Para descubrir el misterio♪
♪We go on adventures♪
♪Nos vamos de aventuras♪
♪We don't run away or compromise easily♪
♪No huimos ni nos comprometemos fácilmente♪
♪When dawn comes♪
♪Cuando llega el amanecer♪
♪The light shines♪
♪La luz brilla♪
♪We follow the path of discovery♪
♪Seguimos el camino del descubrimiento♪
♪To chase and welcome♪
♪Para perseguir y dar la bienvenida♪
♪Every unknown story♪
♪Cada historia desconocida♪
♪We take a trip together♪
♪Hacemos un viaje juntos♪
♪With hot blood and original purpose♪
♪Con sangre caliente y propósito original♪
♪We seize the day and live it to the fullest♪
♪Aprovechamos el día y lo vivimos al máximo♪
♪Leave a mark on our journey♪
♪Deja una huella en nuestro viaje♪
♪Scatter the darkness with our hearts♪
♪Dispersa la oscuridad con nuestros corazones♪
♪Aspire to make a difference♪
♪Aspira a marcar la diferencia♪
♪Make a difference♪
♪Haz la diferencia♪
♪We take a trip together♪
♪Hacemos un viaje juntos♪
♪Through hardships♪
♪A través de las dificultades♪
♪We will find the glory♪
♪Encontraremos la gloria♪
♪Aspire to make a difference♪
♪Aspira a marcar la diferencia♪